and then I will let everybody in from
the lobby. So, we'll need to give it a
minute or two for everybody in the lobby
to join in. Um, as people are coming on
in, good morning everybody. Uh, I am Dr.
Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health. I'm the director
for the Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin. Um, and this is the research
and continuous improvement committee
meeting with Dan Jennings as the chair.
And uh, just as as usual, you will see
most of us with our cameras off through
most of the meeting just to ensure that
there's enough bandwidth for people,
especially individuals who are calling
in from more rural areas or other areas
where uh, internet may be um, uh, may
not be there. But then you will see
those of us who are either presenting or
uh from the do turn on our mics when we
are speaking. Um and when we get to the
point for public comment, we will uh
also have people will be able to raise
their hand um and uh and be able to ask
questions and go through that and we'll
put that information into the chat here
shortly. So with that in mind, uh the
only other part to remind everyone is
these meetings are made public and so
the recordings are put on the website.
So please ensure to use appropriate
language just so that we don't have to
go through and bleep them. Uh which we
will do by the way, but that means that
it takes a lot longer for it then to be
able to get posted on the website
because it has to go through some
additional levels to ensure that it is
appropriate. So, thank you everybody and
with that I turn it over to you Dan.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dom. Appreciate that very
much. Hi everybody. I'm Dan Jennings and
I'm the chair of the research and
continuous improvement committee and
vice chair of the uh psilocybin medical
board. appreciate everybody being here
today and uh this is our time that we
like to just have our introductions for
everybody and we would like to uh have
our introductions from our DO team first
if you wouldn't mind and then we'll go
into the uh introductions of everybody
else that's here on the call. Remember
whenever you're uh ready to make your
introductions just go ahead and raise
your hand. We'll unmute your microphone
then whenever uh we're called on. So
Tom, would you like to introduce your
team?
>> Absolutely. Thank you so much, Dan. Uh
I'm also just putting the information on
how to raise and your hand and unmute in
the chat. So uh for people if you didn't
see it on the screen or not as familiar
with it, that information is also in the
chat. And so um so today from the
department um we have myself uh Dominic
Zerlo. We also have Dr. Robert Truckner
who is our medical director here today.
Uh we have Cyrus Routman who is our
environmental scientist in the
psilocybin program and Leslie Peterson
who is our compliance officer in the
medical psilocybin program. Jorge was
not able to be here today but sends his
regards. We also have Katie Fryag who is
one of our health educators. Uh we have
co Kathy Ajieri who is our project
manager. We have Brenda Martinez who is
our deputy director for the center. Um
and then we have uh Vicente Royel who is
our intern this summer who has been
working with us through this summer and
uh is actually about to wrap up his
internship but has been doing a
wonderful job and uh and we we are sorry
to see him ending his internship but
we're hopefully going to be continuing
with him here in the future. Um, and I
think at this point I caught everybody
from the do side. So, back to you, Dan.
>> Awesome. Thank you all very much.
Appreciate it. And I appreciate our uh
special guest we have today. Uh, thank
you from the board. We have Ian Dunn uh
who is our chair of the psilocidon board
and uh we also have Chris Puscy who just
joined us uh also who is on Silicon
board and uh Senator Steinborn. Thank
you very much for joining us. And for
everybody, please uh feel free to raise
your hand and like I said, we'll come
around and unmute your microphone for
you. Please introduce yourself, your
name, where you're from, uh location, if
you're in New Mexico or not, your
affiliation, if you're affiliated with
anything, and if this is your first time
or if you're returning to the committee
meetings. Appreciate it.
Nathan, go on ahead. You are your mic is
enabled.
>> Great. Thank you. My name is Nathan Oaks
and I live in uh beautiful Lake Tahoe,
California. And um I'm [clears throat]
here to uh talk about a little bit about
data privacy
um and security uh especially with a uh
a little bit of emphasis on
deidentification and reidentification
uh and um this is my first time and I am
uh excited to be here. Thank you guys.
>> Thank you Nathan for being our guest
presenter today and so appreciate you
being here too.
And Don, your mic's enabled.
>> Yes. Good morning. Don Moer, Las Vegas,
New Mexico. And I'm not affiliated with
anyone. I'm just very interested in the
program. Thank you.
Thank you, Don.
And while we're waiting for others to
raise their hand to make an
introduction, I'll read in from the
chat. Uh Kate Hawk, good morning,
everyone. Khawk from Santa Fe trauma
therapist with 20 plus years working
with psychedelic harm reduction Kathy
Sanchez bureau chief at workers
compensation administration medical cost
containment and Hanifeh Washington
co-director of the psychedelic mental
health al access alliance Santa Fe
implementation partner of the UNM groups
psilocybin assisted uh therapy study for
PTSD
and please anybody body else that's on
the call would like to introduce
yourself, please raise your hand and or
drop into the chat box. Also,
we have Gregory Evans, independent
researcher and home ecologist in Santa
Fe
and Sky River, Santa Fe reporter
covering updates on the legalization of
psilocybin from Santa Fe.
and I'll give a little bit more wait
time just in case there's some people
that might still be
doing their introductions.
Okay. Oh, thank you, Nathan Oaks. Uh,
thank you very much for dropping into
the chat box there as well. Um,
appreciate you being here. And actually,
since we have nobody else in the
introduction phase right now, then we'll
go ahead and move into our guest
presentation then with Nathan Oaks. uh
he's a cloud and cyber security engineer
with 30 years of experience designing
and managing secure high resilience
technology systems and man and uh
specially working in development and
operations. He is currently supports
digital health initiatives for US
Department of Veterans Affairs focusing
on cloud architecture, identity and
access management, compliance and
technical risk mitigation specializing
in translating complex security and data
migration
uh issues and uh into actionable
strategies. Nathan bridges the gap
between technical teams, policy makers
and program stakeholders. Today Nathan
will be sharing insights on structuring
the data architecture for our New Mexico
medical psilocybin program and focus on
how we can safeguard participant data
through rigorous privacy controls data
sanity and policy frameworks ensuring
data remains fully identifi deidentified
while and protected while still enabling
vital research continuous quality
improvement and systemwide traceability.
Please help me welcome Nathan.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Dan. Um, I really,
uh, appreciate the ability to be here.
Uh, thank you guys for inviting me. Um,
I want to be clear about the scope of
this talk. I'm not here to prescribe an
entire technical architecture or write a
comprehensive rule set in 20 minutes. My
goal here is to offer a small set of
policy principles and design patterns
that can help New Mexico make those
decisions safely. The core idea is that
this trust by design uh and this is not
primarily a technology problem. It is a
trust and governance problem that
technology then has to implement. Now
I'm approaching this from a systems
cloud security uh data governance
perspective.
uh the gory details can come later but
today I want to focus on the questions
that need to be asked before those
details are built.
So moving on here I I I really want to
make clear before we get into um some
more of the technical stuff
the human stakes why data trust matters.
Privacy here is not just a compliance
requirement. Patient trust can affect
whether people are willing to
participate in the program at all. As we
all know, you know, psychedelic care may
involve some of the most intimate
information a person ever shares.
trauma, mental health history, substance
use, you know, deeply personal
experiences during altered states,
sometimes recording, sensor data, and
you know, yes, breaches can cause
lawsuits, reputational damage,
regulatory consequences, but I don't
want to spend our limited time on
generic breach scenarios. The more
important point for this program is
upstream. If people fear that seeking
treatment will create a permanent
commercially exploitable or government
accessible record of those experiences,
some people will simply avoid treatment.
That's why I'm treating trust as part of
the safety and accessibility model, not
as a public relations concern.
Now the data landscape, today's data and
tomorrow's
uh the rules that we write now can't
really assume that medical data will
continue to look like rows and columns
in electronic health record. As we all
know things move so quickly. Today we
have familiar clinical data. Um,
psychedelic care also creates rich
experiential data like free form
narrative, facilitator observations,
audio, video and you know the frontier
is already moving toward wearables,
biometrics, eye tracking, motion,
neurohysiology,
immersive headset telemetry, AI derived
inferences etc etc. Now some of the
standards that are already written by
federal agencies or NIST or or things
like that uh things have have already
progressed
um past those. And so
I you know I want to make an important
distinction. Uh I'd like to talk about
data minimization but I'd like to make
an important distinction about it. I'm
not arguing that every provider should
collect as little data as possible.
There may be very good reasons with
meaningful patient consent obviously to
capture very rich multimodal data.
Future therapies may use many signals
from a piece experience for instance to
help patients revisit or integrate
aspects of that experience later.
Data minization is important but I think
the better principle
is collect intentionally
expose minimally and use purposefully.
Maximum useful collection doesn't
require maximum exposure.
Policy should separately govern
collection, retention, access, and
disclosure. [clears throat] And it
should regulate categories of risk and
use rather than hard- coding a list of
today's devices or even today's data
fields.
Now, let's move on to deidentification.
I'm kind of presenting a working
vocabulary here. Um, but
deidentification is not a binary thing.
It's not that data is either identified
or deidentified and that's it. There's
somewhat of a spectrum. And I I want to
make clear that these are my working
definitions for this talk. Legal and
technical definitions vary by context.
And obviously New Mexico will be will
will want to write their own clear
definitions of these things. But for the
today's talk, identified data is
directly linked to a person. When we say
pseudonmized uh interesting little word
there um or also what we call relinkable
data means that direct identifiers have
been replaced or separated but an
authorized linkage mechanism still
exists to reidentify that data.
Deidentified data means that the
identification risk has been
deliberately reduced to an agreed level,
but it's not automatically safe. Uh risk
is not necessarily zero. Um there are
multiple ways to to relink that data.
There's things called linkage attacks
and so on. We won't get too far into
that today. Then aggregated data, I
think everyone knows what that means.
That's information that's reported at a
group level. uh but small sets of
aggregated data, small cells can still
create identification risk. And then at
the very end we have anonymized data
which for this presentation means that
no reasonable mechanism remains to
relink that information to a person. Now
risk remains on risk depends on what
remains in the data and what it can be
linked to. The identification is risk
management and not a magic switch. These
terms are often used kind of
inconsistently. Um but I you know I want
to just emphasize that a gooid or a
globally unique identifier something
random that that is linked to uh patient
data for instance doesn't must make that
data anonymous if another system can
resolve that gooid back to a person. The
key point again is that risk depends on
what remains. Dates, locations, rare
attributes, narrative, highdimensional
signals, and and what outside
information can be linked to it. A data
set that is difficult to reidentify
today may be easier to reidentify in the
future. And I have a a fuller glossery
in the backup slides that, you know,
I'll share this slide at the end or this
deck at the end here.
Now, this is really important to me and
I feel like it's very relevant to New
Mexico. You don't need a name to know
who somebody is. They could not have a
name in their data, not have a social
security number, and still be
identifiable.
We call some of these, sometimes we call
these quasi identifiers. Removing names
and numbers isn't really enough.
Ordinary attributes can become
identifying when combined. In New
Mexico, I think this deserves particular
attention because some rural, tribal,
and other communities are small enough
that combinations of age, affiliation,
location, diagnosis, and did that person
have treatment on Tuesday or maybe a
rare event uh may point to one single
person and everybody could know who that
person is even without having
traditional uh identifiable data.
So I would say that we want to treat
this respectfully as a privacy risk
example. Definitely not here as not
bringing this as an attempt to prescribe
tribal level data sovereignity policy.
But um you know I I think that that um
it's difficult to identify what all the
quasi identifiers are. I kind of
anticipate I have had the question many
times like how do I identify all the
quasi identifiers and and the answer
honestly is that we really can't solve
this with a static list. Identifiability
depends on combinations of attributes,
granularity, population size, what
external information is available.
That's why deidentification should
include disclosure, risk assessment, and
reidentification testing, not simply
just removal of fields that we label PII
or personally identifiable information.
And you know from a data security
standpoint we we want to think like an
attacker sometimes but in privacy terms
we say you know given this proposed
release and reasonably available outside
information how successfully could
someone figure out who these people are.
Now there are some um for instance NIST
National Institute of Standards and
Technology special publications that I
that I'll reference in another slide
that I'll share later that deal uh
specifically with this kind of stuff and
there's there's studies and guidance on
this um that New Mexico can refer to.
So security, privacy and governments are
different problems.
So just a little vocabulary here.
Security. When we talk about security,
we're asking who can get to the data.
Privacy asks what can that data reveal
about a person. Data governance asks why
we have the data, who's allowed to use
it, and what they are allowed to do with
it. Now, a system can be extraordinarily
secure. We can have encryption and
identity management and logging and
backups and all the things, but we could
still have a terrible privacy policy if
that organization is permitted to use
patient information for purposes that
patients never reasonably expected.
Now, [clears throat]
just to touch on sock and ISO and and
compliance standards,
I think those can be useful evidence of
an of organizational maturity when we're
talking about, for instance, vendors,
providers in the space, um, that sort of
thing. But these are baselines. They
don't answer New Mexico's core policy
question which is what an organization
should be permitted to do with
psychedelic patient data. Compliance
with SOCK 2 and ISO 27701 and etc is a
floor but trust is the goal.
Now
reidentification of data must be
exceptional and governed.
Here this diagram is just an
illustrative control pattern. It's it's
I'm not suggesting New Mexico mandate a
particular database architecture. Uh the
important concepts here are separation
of identity from sensitive data, least
privilege access policies, separation of
duties, what we call controlled linkage
and very importantly auditability. Now
I'm just giving a pattern here and this
is a possible pattern. Um is an identity
vault separated from clinical or
research data that has a dedicated
linkage service in between ordinary
users almost any nobody should be able
to traverse this entire chain by
themselves. Now for sufficiently
sensitive reidentification New Mexico
could consider dual authorization what
we call the two key pattern kind of like
a nuclear launch. you know both people
have to turn the keys but what that
means in this context is that one person
requests and another independently
approves. This is an established
security control concept. Now there's
some possible legit legitimate
categories and obviously there could be
more but you know for the purposes of
this talk I thinking about patient
directed reidentification possibly for
access to their data correction of data
uh authorized disclosure maybe to other
providers so on um and appropriate
deletion or data withdrawal requests.
Now we obviously have safety and
continuity of care
um which you know could be adverse
events, adverse events, emergency care
coordination or even like product or lot
recall if something's um you know wrong
with a certain lot of product. Obviously
there's also legal and regulatory um
concerns. there's valid legal compulsion
like a subpoena or legal court order um
or narrowly defined oversight.
And
I'll also throw in that there could be
what I call exceptional authorized
research only when identity is genuinely
necessary and appropriate oversight
exists. Now every event, every
reidentification event should be logged
and auditable. Routine patientdirected
events like deletion requests might be
aggregated for oversight. Exceptional
reidentification may merit individual
reporting or prior approval. Now, in an
emergency scenario, we could have a
controlled quote unquote break glass
path that might be appropriate, but
breaking that glass should always create
an unavoidable audit event.
Now this is the ethical core of my
little talk today and
that is that patient data should serve
the patient at at the end of the day.
That's the bottom line. And I think you
know we've all had experiences with
concern being concerned about our data
being sold or used in in ways that we
don't expect or don't want.
You know, this is broader than just
simply saying data cannot be sold. Uh,
you know, a sophisticated business can
monetize information without calling
that transaction a sale.
Uh, they could, you know, licensing,
data brokerage, profile enrichment, what
they what they call that, targeted
advertising, so on and so forth. Um, you
know, or packaging supposedly anonymous
insights from inadequately deidentified
records can can pose a risk. So
companies should absolutely be able to
build successful businesses delivering
treatment um analytics, software,
infrastructure, responsible research
services. But the distinction here is
that the patients intimate information
itself should never become the product.
Purpose limitation is critical.
Information collected for care should
never silently become marketing
unrelated product development or like
general purpose AI training data.
Optional secondary uses should be
genuinely separable where practical. Now
transparency also and I feel like this
is important to all of us and we all can
relate to this. Transparency should be
human readable. A patient should be able
to answer what are you collecting?
Um, why are you collecting it? Who can
see it? Who receives it downstream? How
long is it kept? Can it be used for
research or AI? How do I get a copy of
my own data? How do I request it to be
deleted? When can it be rel to me? Now,
having a legal privacy policy may still
be a good thing, but I think that the
patients should also be receiving a
concise plain language data rights
notice or even a little explainer video.
Um, a privacy right really isn't
meaningful if exercising your privacy
right requires you to become a a privacy
law expert.
>> [clears throat]
>> Now I consider myself a scientist at
heart and I love research and I want to
absolutely enable research in every way
but I want to do that without exposing
people. Um the goal isn't to lock data
away. The goal is to match the
disclosure to the question. And I put
this in kind of a latter format. What I
call progressive disclosure. We start
with the least identifying form of data
capable of answering the legitimate
question, often a research question. If
you need aggregate data, you give the
aggregate. If you need demographic
trends, you give only the demographic
detail that's actually needed. You need
detailed longitudinal
analysis, maybe consider a protected
research environment or maybe a
controlled query model rather than
distributing raw copies all over the
place. Um and then you know if
identifiable data is needed which it
could be in certain cases but that
should require extraordinary
justification.
Now this becomes especially important in
small populations like we talked about
earlier where demographic detail that
feels harmless can become identifying.
Uh again referring to NIST special
publication 800188. They discuss
multiple data sharing models including
deidentified releases, synthetic data,
query interfaces, protected data
enclaves as well as disclosure review
boards, reidentification studies. Now I
think research researchers should divi
derive an enormous value from this
program and will do so. But in most
cases, researchers simply don't need to
know who that participant is.
So I think these are some of the things
that New Mexico should define. Now, now
this is intentionally a set of
questions. It's not a comprehensive rule
book. RECI doesn't need to build the
system today, but it needs to define the
policy boundaries clearly enough that
providers, vendors, researchers,
engineers, etc. can build within them
safely.
Now, the questions here include, you
know, what purposes justify collecting
and using patient data? What uses should
be prohibited outright?
What's the minimum information that
should cross each organizational
boundary?
When can data be reidentified? Who
authorizes that? What must always be
logged and auditable?
What obligations follow the data
downstream
and what rights and explanations must
must patients receive and then you know
crucially how will the rules evolve as
technology changes technology and
reidentification capabilities will
change and are changing. So I would say
to consider mandatory periodic review
um you know on a cadence that's up to
you guys exact cadence for the state to
decide but there also maybe should be a
mechanism for interim guidance to be
issued when technology might be moving
faster than the rule cycle. Again, you
know, SOCK or ISO style standards can be
useful baselines, but New Mexico, I
think, should go beyond checkbox
compliance and define program specific
privacy and data use boundaries.
And I'd like to leave you with this very
simple slide with these three things.
These three objectives don't have to be
in conflict. Protect the person, protect
the data, preserve the value. Now, New
Mexico does not have to choose between
patient privacy and discovery. We don't
have to choose between trust and
innovation. If the rules are built
thoughtfully from the beginning, each
can strengthen the other. Good
governance is what makes responsible
innovation possible because it gives
patients the confidence to participate.
It gives responsible organizations clear
boundaries and it gives researchers
access to useful data without
unnecessarily exposing people. Now today
I've deliberately stayed at the
principal level. There's a a much deeper
layer underneath each of these topics
like disclosure risk risk testing
reidentification controls audit models
research environments
uh vendor requirements you know detailed
policy language. Um, but we're not going
to get to that in in 20 minutes. Um, I
would be happy to help work through
those as the program develops.
Thank you guys. Any uh questions? I
think we have about five minutes left.
Nathan, thank you very much. And while
everybody gets ready for their
questions, you can drop it into the chat
and you can also raise your hand.
Sometimes it's easier to raise hands
because if you have some questions, it's
easier to explain that way. Uh Nathan,
thank you very much for this because we
love uh your presentation here in dactic
because this is part of a travel set of
of dactics we've been having from open
to uh Dr. Pitzky and talking about site
share and things like that. And so as
we're starting to move into this data
collection, I really appreciate uh this
grounding that you've given us with on
really what matters on the data
collection, data reporting, uh the why
uh and the how we can be better stewards
of this information and this data and to
build a really solid. Uh we've talked a
lot about patient safety and this is one
huge part of patient safety. Um so I
would love I mean, this is an
opportunity. If uh anybody has any
questions for Nathan or comments or
thoughts, uh please please raise your
hand, drop them into the chat, and I'll
let you know. Dominic Zeros, thank you,
Nathan. Gregory Evans, thank you, sir.
Um but please, this is this is your time
now.
>> Yeah, Jeff.
>> There we go. There we go. Hey, good
morning everybody and and thank you so
much Dan for the committee and thank you
Nathan for presenting today really
fascinating and something on a lot of
our minds. I have a a lot of questions,
but the one I want to ask you is as we
look at our law, our brand new law, and
if there needs to be any strengthening
or tweaks to it, are is there any It
would be helpful. I'd love your opinion
if you think we need any specific
language in law that further tightens
the protection of data specifically,
you know, any language that kind of sets
more statutory legal sideboards of
ensuring data,
you know, is protected. Um, I think we
have some good protective language in
there now, but I just thought I'd ask
you the question. Thanks. Yeah, you
know, I wish I was more familiar with
the language of the law. Unfortunately,
I hadn't had time to to really review
that. But I mean in answer to your
question um I think that you know in my
mind New Mexico is a leader in this in
this space and other states programs
possibly even other countries are going
to look at New Mexico and they're going
to copy this stuff um or you know use it
in some kind of way. I think it's you
know I put this slide up here from for
selected standards and resources.
There's some really good stuff that NIST
has put out and obviously the the
baselines of ISO and sock. I think those
are good starting points to look at some
of um you know to to look at some of the
language that that could be um in there.
But, you know, I I really feel like New
Mexico needs to go above and beyond
um thinking about trust being built into
the law as as clearly and um you know,
as well defined as as possible. Um I
again I I haven't I don't know the the
the law itself and so that that may a
lot of this may already be in there. Um
but you know an answer to your question
is short answer is yes. I I I think that
it's it's worth looking at and it's
worth really um putting the language of
of trust in there, especially when it
comes to uh patient um patient trust and
concise and and readable um policies
around privacy and things like that. Um
I think it may be just just one thing
off the top of my head. I think it may
be beneficial to include a requirement
that in addition to your standard legal
15-page privacy policy, patients are
provided with a concise human readable,
this is what we're going to do with your
data. These are the cases that in which
it can be reidentified, so on and so
forth. Um, I think that's a good
starting point.
>> Cool. You know, Dan, it would be great
if I don't know if this document's going
to be emailed around, but that would be
really helpful. Um, it's probably worth
saying to everybody on the call, you
know, sometimes, yeah, you define a lot
of these things in rule, so they're not
necessarily specified at this level in
law, but nonetheless,
um, yeah, it's all great feedback and I
and I'm not able to chat for some reason
or or I would have done this, but it
might be helpful if someone can put
SB219 link into the chat
um because it's a pretty short bill and
you could probably see that section real
quick if you were interested. did or
anyone else would love to.
>> Thank you. Thank you so much.
>> Absolutely.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you, Senator. Very, very, very
good point to bring up. I mean, this is
something that Nathan brought up is
because, you know, providers will be
utilizing EMR, EHR, you know, uh,
medical record software in their
organization. And so, this is something
that is not just mindful for the state
side, but also for provider side too.
And I'm glad, you know, Brenda uh is on
the call too. Brenda leads the education
and training committee and so having
some of this information and to speak to
the the document and the slide deck
these will be uh provided uh to do for
the publication up on the website so
that they will be available along with
the uh video recording of this as well
so that way people couldn't make it or
want to refer back to it. Uh and I know
that we have our chair Ian Dunn that has
a question as well.
>> Hey Ian. Yeah, I just wanted to clarify.
So, um, in terms of law, it wouldn't be
data is not very expansively protected
under the medical psilocybin act.
However, um it would still be fall
under, you know, HIPPA and high-tech,
which could help um compliance in terms
of let's not, you know, waste political
capital on um that kind of thing when
especially we can do a lot within this
committee because like like you said, we
should go above and beyond the standards
set in law. Um so what we can do in this
committee is continue that analysis of
how we can keep the our patients as safe
as possible because um you know the
thing about the law is that legislation
is often delayed from reality.
>> So it often takes a lot longer for them
to process things than it does for let's
say bad actors. Um, so by going above
and beyond, especially like I really
liked your presentation, but by going
above and beyond, we can protect against
some of those bad actors and especially
when we have, you know, an expert that
was willing to share with us on cyber
security and that kind of thing. I am
just very um, you know, grateful for the
presentation as a whole and excited to
see how we can actually um,
operationalize all of this. So, thank
you.
>> Yeah, thanks Ian. And, you know, I'm
Fortunately, you know, I'm a cloud
engineer and not a politics guy. So, I
understand that there's a difference
between the law itself as a law and and
then guidance and rules. And so, you
know, I mean, I don't um I you know,
obviously the law is at the top, but it
could point to the guidance and rules
that uh you know, this committee issues.
Um, and you know, I think that, uh,
there's a there's a distinction to be
made there and there's decisions as to
what, like you said, what what kind of
political capital we put into the law
itself. But, um, those guidances, you
know, and and rules that are issued can
can probably move faster than a bill
itself.
>> Great. and Dominic Zarlo put into the
chat the uh link there to uh the statute
there uh for anybody that's interested
as well. So,
>> excellent. All right. Anybody else? All
right. Thank you everyone so much for
the opportunity to share with you guys
today.
>> I end my sharing back to you Dan.
>> Thank you very much Nathan. I really
appreciate your time spending and
expertise that you brought to us today.
this is uh this is huge and so we really
appreciate that opportunity that you
gave us today. Um and please feel free
if you do have time you can stick
around. If you do have to leave we
completely understand. Um just make sure
you just hit the leave button instead of
the the independent button. So
>> you got it. Thanks Dan.
>> Thank you sir. And so um just as a
reminder to us on our next kind of beat
that we're moving into the the racy
subcommittee uh this is kind of what our
guiding principles are. So really to
kind of recenter us back to these kind
of norms again the idea that uh that uh
Nathan brought up about the idea of
being participant centered throughout
this is important. We need to make sure
that we collect what we act on collect
once used many times and we need to make
sure that it's human and not clinical.
So some of the things that Nathan
brought up today, we really appreciate
those reminders back again to us. Uh the
going to our next step, we've been
working on some frameworks in this
committee. Uh this committee's
responsibilities are kind of three-fold.
We have a reporting framework that we're
responsible for. We have a harm
reduction quality improvement framework
responsibility and then a core extended
data set framework. And so Nathan's talk
today was a really good reminder as we
move into that core data set. corks in a
data set to remind ourselves of exactly
why we're doing this and how we need to
do this with good care and protection.
So again, the three intersectional work
groups that were created were care and
pathway and safety, participant
experience, fit and data reporting and
architecture and those are headed up by
uh three individuals that usually are
here. I'll say that uh Danielle Leonard
is one of those could not make it today
uh and Dr. James Brown was not able to
make it today and Gregory Evans who is
on the call today. So just so you know
that that those kind of intercession
work groups happen outside of these so
that that way we can get a lot of this
big work going and then they're brought
back to the committee so that we can
discuss and come to consensus on that.
So one of our first was a breakdown for
those three uh inter session workg
groupoups and this was to create that
reporting framework task. And so these
were kind of the the task breakdowns
that each one of those uh workg
groupoups were working on and then
brought back to our committee uh which
if you uh were able to sign up before uh
a few days ago, you received a copy of
this deck just to kind of look at in
advance. Again, if you didn't receive
it, it will be published on the DOH
website after this meeting. But just so
you can see that on the 12th of June,
the subcommittee here uh came to
consensus that these are the kind of uh
reporting framework [clears throat]
areas that we're interested in making
sure that there was information for. So,
seven different areas uh divided up into
before the session, then the session
itself, and then after the session,
including an early follow-up, which is
usually defined about 24 to 72 hours
after the uh session. And so, these were
the categories that we were looking at
as kind of the information that we would
like to have and to look at and to work
on. That then moved into the harm
reduction quality improvement framework.
And this was the task breakdown for
those three work groups that started to
work on and really especially started to
work on the event tiers for uh for not
just adverse or serious adverse
reactions but also challenging
experiences. So today for this part of
this work group I would like to present
to you what the work groups have come up
with. U so we'll present it here for the
first time. Again, if you did have a
copy of this ahead of time, you got to
see this so that we can have good
discussion today. But today, what I
would like to do is present and then
have feedback and then ultimately if we
can come to a consensus to see if we're
good with this or what changes we need
to make. So I'll present these four
different tiers and two different
reporting pathways for the harm
reduction quality improvement framework.
So first one is that a session would be
a tier one routine no incident. This is
essentially what we're hoping for for
100% of all sessions that there are no
safety concerns, no unexpected
deviations from care plan. So therefore,
this is simple, very simple things that
might happen during any kind of
psilocybin experience. And so therefore,
there would be no specific individual
incident report required, reporting
required. Uh, however, let's move to a
tier two, which is a challenging
experience because we've heard a lot. We
when we first started this workg group
uh committee uh everything I looked at
was adverse experience. So actually
working through a lot of the
conversations that y'all have provided
and for example Dr. Pitzky and his work
we really decided let's look at a tier 2
which is challenging experience. This is
something that may come up during the
session it may come up during
integration. Uh and these are things
that uh really can be managed within the
session container for example like grief
processing, transient paranoia or fear
or those kind of feelings of getting
stuck or feeling crazy or things like
this. Uh any kind of like mild physical
discomfort um that might require some
hands-on or some support in the session
but usually resolves naturally. Uh also
even going to an anxiety or emotional
intensity that may still continue but
usually resolve next day during that
initial uh uh quick uh intervention that
can come up during that first kind of uh
check-in and then participant that might
have any kind of difficulty but then at
the end says no I feel safe and I feel
supported. So really what we wanted to
do is just make sure that internally
those things were documented because
that would be part of the facilitation
process uh in data. It could just be a
yes no flag entered and so it would just
look at trend monitoring. That would be
all those kind of things we look at. But
this would not be something that needs
to get reported back into program but
just something that we could look at for
quality improvement purposes.
And then that [clears throat] leads into
the higher tier tier three. this is an
adverse or ae experience and it does
have some clinical significance. So a
tier three would be negative unexpected
negative outcomes that uh last beyond
the session in some cases and require
intervention beyond standard support.
And so we broken it down into two
physical and psychological. So physical
things might be like nausea or vomiting
that that requires medical attention or
uh causes dehydration or headaches and
migraines that do not respond to
standard treatment. Uh blood pressure
that requires medical evaluation but it
is not an emergency that's another tear
up. Uh allergic reaction but is not
anaphilaxis. Uh and then going into
psychological things like this that
panic persists after 72 hours even after
you have postsession uh support sleep
disruption that lasts for more than a
week. Uh worsening of the mental health
conditions um such as PTSD symptoms um
that even the participant feels harmed
or dismissed or invalidated during the
session and that the participant feels
that has a lasting impact on their
well-being.
>> [snorts and clears throat]
>> uh HPPPD or also DPDR depersonalization
derealization
um and that could last on you know
within 48 hours but then could persist
uh disorienting depression or even the
onlogical shock or that fear of
existential dread that might happen that
doesn't resolve through standard
integration. So these are things that
are just classified as what tier two or
tier three adverse experience and there
is what we are recommending a mandatory
entry into the the state system somehow
that has to be done within 5 days and
then uh there is facilitator
documentation. uh it would require
quality improvement um system learning
reviews because these kind of things
might be something that we just don't we
want to uncover and see if there's
something that can help in uh future
rule changes or best practices and
things like that. Um and this is even
that after those initial sessions and
into those integration follow-up
sessions would follow the same pathway.
Then into tier 4 these would be the SAE
serious adverse uh events and these do
require external responses and uh formal
review. So what this comes into are
things like there's three different uh
three different areas that we're looking
at. Medical emergencies, uh psychiatric
emergencies, and also safety and conduct
events. So for the first two that we
have here, I just wanted to also kind of
call out to this is that we understand
that there are individuals that will be
in the program that
have uh that that have like terminal
endstage. uh they're at the end of life
as their as their criteria for being the
program. So we just want to make sure
that that these are not specific to
those events that are consistent with
their disease trajectory. Um so just so
you know this is for individuals that
would be outside of those kind of things
that these are outside of the
expectations of the session. So these
would be cardiac events, hypertensive
crisis, uh seizure activity,
anaphilaxis, loss of consciousness that
requires airway management, uh or any
medical event requiring ER or
hospitalization. And then same for
psychiatric because we know that at EOL
that somebody might just say might have
these conversations about death and
dying and having a good death. So again,
this does not necessarily mean suicidal
ideiation. So therefore, individuals
that are not at EOL, if there is
suicidal ideation with plans, then those
are things that need to come into an SAE
report. Uh self harm, uh acute psychotic
break, prolonged psychosis, and
homicidal ideiation. And then for the
last uh part of tier 4, safety, uh and
events. So we really want to make sure
the patients are safe and feel safe. So
things that might be like patient
alopment during the session where they
could be uh acutely uh impaired. So that
would be something that would be an SAPE
uh boundary violations from provider
participant disclosure of abuse uh
facilitator practicing outside of scope
or training uh facilitator impairment uh
medication errors. And so the reporting
actions that we have for this is that
that's an immediate uh report within 24
48 hours and formal investigation
required. Um it this also looks at
credentials uh that might be initiated
and uh just uh to be clear patients are
informed of the department of health
reporting channel uh and offered uh
different advocacy supports. So these
this is kind of what we're looking at
for the tier 4. And so I kind of
previewed this DO reporting channel. So
we're looking at two different reporting
channels. One is through the
facilitator. That's the primary
reporting channel. And these are the
things that come in to the facilitator
that would be uh reported. But we also
want to ensure that there is an
escalation and especially for sensitive
that could be a DO direct. So these
would be reserved for these kind of
things like boundary violations where
the participant feels unsafe. um that uh
they can report directly to the DO and
that does kind of trigger a tier three
or tier four review if it comes in
through that way. So
this is kind of what the the work groups
have come up with to present to us here
today and um after going through it I
would love to hear everybody's comments,
feedback um are we on a mark? Have we
missed the mark? Um and then as we come
to the end I would like to be able to
see or if we didn't but we missed the
mark completely we'll come back and
revise if it's something that um that we
might be able to move forward with we
would love to kind of work moving
forward into this. So please during this
time uh please raise your hand if you
can if you can't you can drop into the
chat box whatever you would like to do
on this. So, thank you. And first one,
Ian.
>> Hi, thank you. Um, love the document. It
was very well thought out and clearly
they spent a lot of time um, working on
it. One question I have is um, this is a
very named perils type of document.
What about
situations that we don't know
like um
current like adverse events that we
don't predict, right? So if there was
some sort of outside of this list
adverse event, let's say um a patient
didn't eat for 4 days, right? Where
would that patient be reported?
>> Right? So to try to and to try to catch
those kind of things, we've broke down
into these tiers. So for example, that
would not be let's say that the patient
didn't eat for several days ahead of
time and thus had some sort of an event.
So it wouldn't be a tier one. So then it
would be the facilitator practitioner
that would make or the the fac the
practitioner would say, is this a is
this a challenging experience? Meaning
could is this something that got
resolved during the session container?
um if it was something that I didn't eat
and so I felt weak and and so I didn't
feel good but as an example I'm just
saying uh then the individual then had
something to eat in in in the session or
right during that integration time uh
and it resolved itself then that would
probably be listed as a tier 2
challenging experience because it
happened but it required some support
and it resolved itself in that
container. However, if it was something
that required uh it was a little bit
more, it had some clinical significance.
So, they had like a a sugar crash and it
required maybe some intervention from
some medical. For example, if they have
insulin, they administered insulin to
themsel, that might be an adverse event
with clinical significance because it
was something that wasn't necessarily
inside of the container and required
some sort of some physical example that
took place there. However, if it was in
in this example that the person did not
have insulin and it didn't resolve
itself through through having something
to eat during that session, uh then it
required a hospitalization or required
EMS. And this would be an SAE in that
example. So, we tried to kind of bring
those three tiers like that into where
you could kind of categorize those kind
of things that are not specifically
called out in those bullet points. I
hope that helps. And if it doesn't, let
me know and say that nope, it needs to
be more clarified or or here's another
just as example.
>> No, that works. That actually makes a
lot more sense. I had kind of spent a
lot of time reading the bullet points
and not looking at the the phrase at the
top. But yeah, that makes a lot of sense
based on what intervention is needed,
right? Because it's going to be a lot
different if, let's say, they had low
blood sugar, right? if they just need um
candy versus if we need to get dextrose
like that is um two ends of how serious
it was and how um we could handle it. So
yeah, I support the adverse reporting
system as it stands. It's very well
thought out. Thank you.
>> I appreciate you saying that. Yeah, it
it is something where we knew that if we
just listed those the top part that we
wouldn't get into the detail, but also
by having some of those details then you
can get to the point where the detail is
not detailed enough for everything. So
hopefully it gives a little bit and
honestly to be to be very honest this is
something that during u like facilitator
preparation these are great things that
the training can bring up. So just like
you called out, it's like okay you know
facilitators practitioners if this
happened how would this be handled and
so I think with good education and
training in the dactic and the practicum
I think we can get that very clear with
everybody in the pro I feel
uh Kate Hawk said good work thanks to
everyone who worked on this. Thank you
Kate. Uh Brenda
Your mic isn't
>> Hello. Hi. Um, my mic wasn't working. I
wanted to thank Nathan for his um his um
presentation on you know keeping things
uh secure. Um that was a real big safety
thing for many people. And thank you Dan
for this. This is really um wonderful
because this just gives us more
information for education and training
to um put that um in there because I
think often times especially um people
who have never experienced that with a
client uh this is very important and
also too um what's going to be happening
as well this is what I imagine is that
you're going to have a team of people so
if someone isn't having an adverse
reaction during their session, however,
maybe soon afterwards and and doing our
due diligence and and telling the the
patient, "Hey, if you're feeling off, if
you're feeling kind of panicky or
anything like that, please call us." Or
if you want us to check in 24 hours
after you come home, let us know. so
that we're doing our due diligence for
continuing uh the care that needs to be
for um uh an individual. So Dan, I want
to thank you and your team for having
all of this information because this is
very important uh for education and
training. We want people to be um
well-versed in this area especially um
because we want to be able to like
Nathan said go over up and above what
we're used to actually. And so this is
um this is wonderful. I can't get into
the chat for some reason. If I'm stone
quiet, it's usually because I can't get
into the chat or someone's already
brought up the subject before I can even
get in. So, uh, I want to just thank
everyone for their hard work on this.
>> Thank you very much for the good words
on that, Brenda. Yeah, I have to say
that the, uh, leaders of these three
work groups and then all the people that
are working with them on this because,
and I apologize not being recognizing
everybody's name. So, I'm going to
always forget the specific individuals
that are working on this, you know,
offline. So, please, if you're on the
call today and you're like, "Hey, I have
to work on this." I really need you to
either, you know, raise your hand and
say it if you can't get in the chat or
put it in the chat because seriously,
this is again I this is not me. Uh I
always like to say that it's great to be
a conductor of an orchestra because
people think that guy's doing all the
work. I'm not doing anything. I'm just
up here. Everybody else is doing the
work. And so they have done amazing
things on this. And I want to call out
what Danielle really wanted to hit in
this, which is what you called out,
Brenda, which was, and that's what I've
got on the screen there, harms
identified practitioners at scheduled
follow-up integration. So, for example,
this might be after that initial that
after that initial 24 48 hours of just
quick initial check-in that these kind
of things will come up because there are
slow building arms that can come up that
the participant might stop. And so we
don't want to just like, well, if I
didn't hear from the didn't hear from
the patient, I guess everything's going
awesome for them. We really want to
build the best practices into the
program so that the practitioners and
facilitators are reaching out to the
patients to hear back from them because
we we don't want to just assume great
things. I mean, great, but that's where
we start to have serious issues there,
too. So, uh, Greg
Greg, your mic is enabled.
>> Hey, good morning. How's everyone?
There's a lot of information.
Um, something that Danielle and I
discovered um or kind of like we're
working through recently around tier 4
delineation is that it might be useful.
I don't know if this got it to the notes
for today, but [clears throat]
it might be useful to have an event
class that essentially tells us what
happened. Whereas like conduct and
ethics events should remain eligible,
not mandatory, but eligible for tier 4
because they may require immediate DO
review like participant protection or
credential action. But they should be
separated as an event class in the data
model. An event class tells us what
happened like a psychotic break or a
medication error or a incidence of
sexual misconduct. Those might all be
tier 4, but they're not exactly the same
analytic category.
Yeah, thanks for calling that. That's I
think one of the reasons why um there
were these kind of things like medical
emergency, psychiatric emergency and
safety and cognitive event and so the
granularity of the specificity of what
is happening is dependent upon the data
set that uh will be proposed you know by
y'all. So, for example, it could be as
simple as saying it was a medical
emergency and then a and more like an
open field or a psychiatric emergency
and an open field andor safety and
conduct in an open field. Uh, or it
could I don't like Ian made a very good
comment on that because if it is like a
drop- down checkbox thing, there are
things that might be missed. So I I am
kind of ambivalent on both of those two
things because one is great to have very
clean data set and then one is you miss
out vice versa. So just I I think that
as you move into this third phase, the
third and final phase that we're working
on, that's where you all get to say
here's how we really want to have that
and here's the reason why.
>> Yeah, that was a little breadcrumb for
[laughter]
>> Yeah, for it's it's the teaser for the
next part. So yes, great. Thank you very
much, Gregory. And again, thank you for
you and your team on working on this
because again, this was some of the
things that really started to come out
from the work that had been like
bubbling underneath all this stuff. Um,
and it was great to have, you know, like
I said, all of y'all's Danielle's and
Dr. Browns and your expertise. And I
think that Kate was part of this process
as well. I know that Kate hasn't said
anything in there, but I know that
Kate's been part of this. There's been
several people that have been bringing
these kind of things in. So that's why
it's comprehensive and and and I think
beautiful for that reason. But I would
love to hear from other people out there
as well that are on the call to say like
okay uh if there's any like I said kind
of push back something that we missed
because this is the time this is a
really good time to do so before I would
ask for a like a consensus vote.
>> Yes. Yeah. The only thing I'm curious
about um and it's more of a hope for the
best uh prepare for the worst is I don't
want someone who is opposed to the
program to say there are a lot of
serious adverse events happening in the
program and it has nothing to do with
how we've regulated it or what's
illegal. it it's just there was bad
actors. For instance, boundary
violation, romantic initiation, that
kind of thing. Um, and I don't think we
should lump those together cuz I don't
want them to say, "Well, this is
dangerous. This is a the medicine can't
be here because there are all these
serious adverse events." Um,
when in reality, the medicine is very
safe. um sometimes
hopefully not there are bad actors in
any field um and I don't know it may be
such a moot point cuz I don't know if it
will actually appear um but it's just
something for consideration. No, I and
actually what you just said echoes
really what Gregory was just talking
about. The idea being if we just put it
all into one data element and say we had
14 tier 4 saes that is not granular
enough in order to take action based
upon that. So the idea of being able to
say okay we had 14 tier four but they're
broken into this many medical
emergencies this many psychiatric
emergencies and this many like
participant safety conduct violations
then you actually have a little bit it
is what I'm thinking a little bit better
opportunity then to review take action
but also on the public side because then
it is like okay these are things and
then you get to go into if it was a tier
4 safety and uh uh conduct event then
it's like then what happens you know
that's the really sapes
are everything's going to happen across
the board we then need to also be very
conscious about the data to say then
what was happened what happened within
this period of time 24 4872 this
happened an investigation this happened
maybe it was a license issue that was
then uh clarified that that person lost
their license or and then
[clears throat] continued into it could
even go into uh uh adjudication. So I
think that you're calling out something
that is very clear that needs to be
addressed when we go into the court
extended data set so that you're exactly
right. It's not just lumped all together
but just like Gregory said separated out
in some way. I I hope that helps explain
and I hope it kind of is it something
that sounds like that could help there.
I think again it's a prepare for the
worst situation. So I'm imagining right
like someone who just hates the idea of
psilocybin. Um and so they would just
say well there's serious adverse events
all over the place. It is a horrific
thing. Um and if those are like conduct
related to a specific facility, right,
and that's where they're racked up.
Sure, we could go adjudicate and we
could say, well, this is what was
actually happening, but oftent times
what makes the headline is number of
serious adverse events due to
psilocybin, right? Um, but I do think
that overall we do you did a good job or
Gregory and um James and all of the
others that participated um did a really
good job. It's just in a prepare for the
worst kind of situation. And honestly,
again, this could be a moot point in
that we we could have a perfect program.
You know, none of us can predict the
future. Maybe we have no bad actors.
Maybe psilocybin just makes people not
have bad choices. Um, I doubt that
because I have still made a bad choice
after, but um,
just kind of spitballing and throwing it
out there just so that there is a point
of conversation cuz Greg kind of pointed
it out and I wanted to just explore that
that other avenue cuz there is still a
lot of, you know, stigma and there is
still a lot of societal perception that
we have to work against and I don't want
that to be shaped by incomplete
information if people are being served
like that. But again, we can't predict
the future and maybe we shouldn't try to
protect against something that we don't
know could even happen. We don't know
how the reporters would do it, how um
that marketing would happen. But um
yeah, overall I still think this is a
great system all in all. um even if it
was to stay under tier 4 like I would
still support it as a whole cuz I think
the data collection mechanisms are um
structurally sound and rooted in patient
response and safety. So I think it is
great overall that was just response and
chatter. Thank you.
>> No, this is like I said this is exactly
why I want to have this there. There's I
always like to say there's you know you
called it a moot point. I don't think
so. I think that when you're feeling
that, you call that out and this is
something that it exists there for a
reason. So, we need to like if if there
is something we can change or make a
difference or or adjustment in, yes, we
definitely can. And it and you're right,
it might be something that never comes
up. It might be something that we need
to to do. Uh but yeah, absolutely. Uh
and then I know that we got Jason really
impressive. Sky, well done. And then
Styles said, "I think this information
needs to be shared, but I do agree with
and Gregory,
>> I just curious if you wanted to lump
[clears throat] uh get into the feedback
loop before we move on or do you want to
because it's it's
[clears throat] could be relevant here,
but it could be other because I know we
want to codify this um today.
Um but some of the things people are
asking kind of lead us to how how is the
feedback loop and the interpretation of
the data going to be handled.
So up to you on that Dan.
>> Well uh I think on the feedback loop
because that is not in my perview that I
see today but that doesn't mean I don't
want it brought up. So I'm like if you
can bring that up a little bit and share
about that. Now it's not part of the
exor extended data set
>> [clears throat]
>> uh part of this or is it part of that?
>> I think it's outside of the schema. It's
more of an operational thing
>> like what does the system do with a harm
signal after it's collected
>> and what are the loops for those for
monitoring and responding to those
outputs.
>> No, I think that that would be um
something to bring up uh at this point.
So yeah, you might be able to hit it for
a couple of minutes. That would be
great.
>> Um I think [sighs and gasps]
>> Sure. Uh we got Who's got their hand up
there? Don.
>> Don.
>> I will defer to Dom for a moment.
>> Well, thank you, Greg, and thank you,
Dan. I I just want to I mean first of
all this is just really excellent the
work um that's gone into this and it
really does fit very well with some of
the things that have already been
proposed and some of the things already
incorporated in including for example in
some of the things with for example you
uh talk is it on this slide or the last
one where it talks about toxicity. So
for example if there's a contaminant in
the product where there's a a process
for recall and for testing and things
like that. So like these kinds of things
really do fit in with it. And in the the
proposals that we've really been moving
forward and looking at, it does include
the reporting with regard to adverse
events. Um just to let everybody know,
we wouldn't put the specific items about
adverse events into rules because those
can change, but they would be in
guidelines and best practices. So just
when people see that, a lot of times
people think the rules have like every
single tiny detail in it and they don't
necessarily. But what I want to walk
through is kind of an idea of uh to give
what would sort of happen when a report
like this came in because it's the same
kind of process we really use any time
anytime we get adverse events reported.
It's the same similar process to what we
used when uh with for example when we'd
get reports with regard to cannabis for
example. Um like if uh you know if we
got reports on mold at a a cannabis
facility what would sort of happen and
what essentially occurs is uh and and
actually Dan if you go back to the last
slide you kind of have it or it might be
the slide before that. Um yeah there you
go. So the action so where it gets if
you look at the bottom of the slide it
sort of outlines it I think pretty
clearly um and what would happen is once
do is notified in that short time frame
we investigate sometimes it may be
something that you know there's an
adverse event that has nothing to do
with anything the practitioners did or
anything else maybe it was a situation
you know just uh that that's for example
the the participant the patient may have
had a heart condition that was
undisclosed and unfound prior to it. But
what would essentially happen is that
investigation into what are the causes
or potential causes for this happening.
Um we have done before for example with
regard to cannabis where we had
providers who were not doing the
appropriate review, not doing the
appropriate things and they then their
their licens and credentials that report
was sent over to their licensing board
and we have had providers who have
gotten sanctioned or fined by their
licensing board. That part is up to
their licensing board but the department
facilitates that sort of report going
over there. So, just as an example,
those safety factors are are already in
place and they're actually standard
procedures. You won't really see that a
lot in the rules because it's part of
standard procedures in those kinds of
cases. And in those cases, we do defer
while we gather the evidence. It then
gets deferred to the appropriate
licensing board. And then the
participants of course are informed of
the information. For example, if it was
a toxicity or contaminant issue with the
product, we have that entire process of
the product getting recalled and
destroyed. Well, tested first obviously
and then if necessary destroyed or just
to make sure it's not something with
that, where could that contamination
have come in? For example, was it at the
production facility? Was it during
transport? Was it at the actual healing
center or the practitioner's office?
Those sort of things. So there would be
that kind of an investigation and so
depending exactly on what was found
would really depend then on the next
steps. So whether it's a you know a an
accidental sort of contamination like in
that case I'm talking about you know um
then it's about a destroy make sure that
you know what has happened there's
what's called a notice of contemplative
action which would mean like in that
case whoever wherever the contamination
happened they'd have to put in place a
protocol and demonstrate that that was
is not something that will happen again
in the future and of course if it's
severe enough it actually could result
in the pulling of their permits. And so
it all depends sort of what's found in
that investigation. But that gives you
an idea of how that works. And we're
we're that's something that's a thread
throughout all of the rules as they move
forward. And so we already have that
within with regard to the cultivation
with and the laboratories. We have that
already built in in part and are
continuing to build it in as far as for
the patients and the providers and
education. And then it will continue as
we go through other changes and
additions into the rules. For example,
another one that's not actually in here,
but say for example, it's a serious
event. I mean, not a serious event, but
is a data breach. Similar process and
procedures with regard to that. So, as
Nathan was talking a lot about is we
want to protect that data. Well, if
there's a data breach, we have to do an
a a a an entire investigation to ensure
see what happens. I'm sure we've all at
some point gotten those letters from
like such and such financial institution
had all of this. We have those sort of
things will be in place to be able to
notify patients to be able to notify
providers etc. So hopefully that helps
to explain a little bit of what happens.
Um and to kind of give an idea of
something that could happen and how we
would respond.
>> Thank you, Dom. That is yeah, this
because I knew that there were probably
already avenues in place at the DO and
ultimately these kind of things bubble
up to the DO level to to take care of in
whatever way. But as you said, it could
also be the licensing boards. It could
be lots of other places too.
Oh, and Dan, just one more thing, and
it's also really important, and it was
on one of the slides as well, which I
thought was really great, is that it
also has to be that it's not just
potentially the providers, practitioners
who are reporting, but the patients
themselves um and even their family
members. So, for example, you may have a
patient who says, um, say they're
getting really vivid dreams for the week
or two afterwards, cuz that was on one
of the earlier slides, and they don't
want to say anything because they're
minimizing it themselves. Then, the the
family members, spouses, etc. would be
able to also report. And so to have a
mechanism for that sort of thing to
happen so that it can actually ensure
that you know the patients are being
taken care of and that problematic
situations are addressed. Yeah, that
that was one of the things that the
group was really interested in in making
sure it it was there in that container
because that's why we put on there do
triages the report and determines
whether it's a tier three or a tier 4
because it could be something like oh
that was just those kind of ontological
those dreams those kind of things not a
tier 4 SAE but it was an adverse
experience because it persisted past the
uh and it affected the the the group the
individual the group in some way so that
is an adverse and I again going back to
you know some of the things like Ian
brought up is like yes I understand that
that could be something where the
headline could be grabbed and say these
are adverse experiences and so we just
need to be very clear uh in this also so
that people don't just grab the
sensationalism but you also can't help
unfortunately with those kind of things
too but uh we want to say that those
were outside of the challenge experience
they were more adverse in that case and
So, record hope that helped also to
clarify the feedback loop too.
>> Yeah, totally. Uh, I didn't mean to run
a yarn. [clears throat] Um, I did want
to speak. I love that um point that was
just brought up and
trying to figure out uh like like types
of solutions that go back to treatment
where if there if we have
a way for we create an easy way an easy
path for people who are experiencing
complicated
post- psychedelic experiences like heavy
dreams right if the practitioner is
involved in that loop in a in an
immediate if the um the licensed
provider is there hearing those things
from the participant in real time or
closer to real time and preventing that
um pathway for allowing something that
could become a very positive experience.
things we learn from our dreams if we're
doing that work versus some the pathway
where that becomes consuming and turns
into a psychotic episode.
having a way for the program to um
tighten that communication loop during
the extended the early and extended
process of integration
um and ongoing
[snorts] pathway of folding these
experiences into that individual's life
and that's more of like a how do we
technology this stuff but anyways we
should land this
>> no that's appreciate you brought up
because again I think that a lot of it
is like how do we handle how do we deal
with what any of these kind of
experiences are that gets reported to
the practitioner or to the do. So
absolutely that is clearly part of that
uh feedback cycle that you're talking
about there. Um so on this uh I would
since I don't see any more hands or
comments in the chat on that. So I would
love it if we because I do like to get
consensus before we move forward with
saying like great we build consensus on
this because it's just proposed right
now. So, if you're uh from New Mexico,
because again, part of our norms are
that New Mexicans get to vote on this.
If you're from New Mexico, uh on the
call, please raise your hand if you feel
strongly that we move forward and build
consensus with this uh harm reduction
quality improvement framework. And then
I'll ask for a show of hands if you
don't. So, for those right now, a show
of hands if you do want to build
consensus and move forward with this
Thank you all. And if you wouldn't mind
lowering your hands now, we have eight.
And then for
the next question, I'll ask
see when when Skype
There we go. And then this would be for
No, if you do Oh, Sky, your hand is up.
So, oh, I'm sorry. I just want to see if
you did have a comment or question. So,
and then for this next part, I would
like to ask if there is anybody a show
of hands that does not want to move
forward with this proposed framework.
See, no hands raised for that. And I
appreciate everybody that built the
consensus around that. We will go ahead
and mark this down as something. Yay.
All right. Great. We've got Yeah, I
know. Yeah, that's great. I love that,
too. It's like that's the one thing I
love moving forward with something. So,
thank you all very much for this. This
it's a huge because again, honestly,
this is this is this is great to be able
to to to to take what all of y'all have
worked together on all these months and
move forward with it. So, thanks again.
And that leaves us into our uh last
little beat here for our uh committee
meeting which is the core extended data
set. Again I keep referring back to this
because this is the last real part that
we're tasked with during this time is to
recommend core and extended data set and
I call it that because there are certain
data elements that we know that are
going to be like critical for the entire
program. There are others that could be
classified extended. Great for research,
great for um potential um uh uh optional
reporting, but these are the things that
we just want to try to fair it out. So
again, the three work groups have been
kind of assigned uh these kind of uh
task breakdowns. So the care pathway and
safety and participant experience and
fit both of those two uh work groups get
to really look at how do you define in
data these kind of things because a lot
of this is some are feeling based and
some so it's hard to really kind of grab
around those kind of things. So those
work groups are going to talk about how
we can in data capture some of these
kinds of things. And then of course the
biggest one the the third work group
which is the data reporting and
architecture. Um these are the ones that
really define and this is just an
example doesn't mean that this is the
data set but again these are just some
things that from hearing and talking to
people that this might be some of the
things that we as data elements we
collect. So again the group has to
decide what is the required minimum
elements and what are those enhanced the
extended data elements. And um the the
hope the expectation at this point is
that September 11th uh from our next uh
workg group that we are a committee
hearing that we have here will be that
time that it will be presented. And so
we'll talk about it at that time. Again
hopefully you know we'll have it a
little bit ahead of time. I'll be able
to push that out to everybody that is
registered for the meeting so you can
look at it and talk about it. But we'll
basically spend a lot of that whole
meeting going over those things, talking
about it and building that kind of
consensus as well. U and so I like I
said I know that uh Danielle couldn't
make it and neither could uh Dr. Brown,
but Gregory, did you want to share a
little bit about the work that y'all are
doing on this part with everybody?
And Greg, your mic is enabled.
>> Sure.
>> It's a lot of data, isn't it? It's like
just a lot of questions to ask people.
It's like a [laughter]
I [clears throat] think I don't know.
I'm really interested in
um
actually Dan before I lay into
a wall of text uh is there any
particular areas you want to highlight
today?
>> Uh no I just know that um the the
September 11th meeting will be where uh
this will be kind of presented what the
core or extend data set looks like. So I
know that there's nothing to like hey
we've got this already. So, I just
wanted to kind of uh have you at this
time share if there's anything that you
wanted to say like we're working on this
or we're stuck on this especially this
is a good time to maybe um if there's
put like your email address out there so
that if people wanted to join this
interession workg group that y'all are
working on uh for feel free to drop that
in there as well. But that's kind of
where it's just just real quick like
maybe any any five minutes or so would
be good.
>> Yeah, that was cool. Um just
[clears throat] kind of the heads. Um
the core and data extended framework
consensus is an interesting question
because it links directly into the the
technology framework and [clears throat]
how the reporting is executed. and will
define what becomes a burden and what
becomes um actionable uh data that we
can have flexible analytics on. The
idea of having core data sets that are
kind of required and then
an open list of other buckets where we
can receive information if people choose
to report on certain things. allows for
uh the independent structure of
somebody's business to have the
flexibility. We're not trying to tell
companies and healers and whatnot like
exactly what instruments they need to
use to define something in a clinical
uh framework. But um [clears throat] one
of the interesting things that came up
for example was the difference between
um using the I think it was Oasis versus
GAD 7 as a preferred anxiety measure and
just allow like if our data architecture
allows for both of those and we say we
need to receive an anxiety measurement
here are options or you can submit your
own. Like that's a
question about architecture that can't
be really like we can't define the
request and the requirement until we
have some level of understanding what
the capacity of the system that's
receiving and transmitting that
uh health record.
Um
it's not the like the idea that the
battery is not as much of an
administration plan. It's more of like a
pool validated pool of validated
measures that are acceptable for
receipts um sorted by purpose, burden,
trigger, and pathway.
Um, moving [clears throat] into
the
data dictionary side of things is
something that we've been that we will
be working tirelessly on. Like that's
[clears throat] I think the data
defining the data dictionary and what uh
alignment is needed for different tools
is kind of a big chunk of that work. And
um we've been in discussion with Pitzky
since that last me meeting. And
[clears throat] not to get too deep into
the concept of his program that he
brought up called Syshare. P S Y share
um
we discovered that he doesn't actually
like that system is more of a unifier.
So like it c it kind of takes other
people's schema and will unify it into
deidentified or anonymous reporting
tools that are accessible to
um you know a public or a wider market
of researchers. Um we need to decide
what type of uh systems we align with
where those boundaries are and how that
information is protected.
we [clears throat] don't necessarily
need and this is an interesting question
to define uh around metadata alignment.
Um [clears throat] that specific tool
that we're investigating there um
doesn't specifically need that metadata
alignment, but that doesn't mean that we
don't need to define what our
architecture is. [clears throat] And
then
uh the last thing we wanted to kind of
plug
Well, there's two more things.
When we're capturing screening data,
defining what type of like therapeutic
alignment measures we if we're going to
find if we're going to measure or review
things like practitioner or or provider
and p and participant alignment, we need
to gather certain things
um from the
uh screening portion of the process.
We're we're measuring like the efficacy
of the idea is to measure the efficacy
of the entire containment of care. So
it's not about the dosage day. It's
about how was everything planned. What
how was the alignment
uh perceived by each end of the system?
Whether that's three or four people
involved in that measure or if it's just
like the patient saying, "Ah, that was
okay. I didn't really like my shaman
today.
Um and yeah, so capturing that screening
data and what screening data is captured
is pretty um interesting conversation
that we hope to get into. And then the
in inside of that um
we have begun to discuss the idea of in
including insurance readiness. So like
how prepared are our uh providers to
handle the needs of the
the infrastructure of payments and if
they're if we have providers that are
using certain uh
I don't like I don't I'm not an
insurance person but like if we
[clears throat] have people pushing back
on pre uh pre-approved conditions or
stuff like that like We want to be able
to identify like where the easiest paths
are and then feed though that
information back into training and
education so when providers are getting
educated on the process of dealing with
this complicated system in the state of
New Mexico that we can create pathways
for ease and that's kind of bringing
back the review cycle from the research
and comm research and continuous
improvement
uh where the value of crosswalking
information to other departments and
other uh pillars can be super
beneficial. I think that's about it.
>> That's fantastic. Thank you very much
and glad you brought up that the site
share with Dr. Bliski and how that
operates because again as we move
forward with the program um I know that
the research field is going to be very u
uh it's going to be something that we
really need to look at and how can the
data that we're collecting in this
program be shared. So hearing that and
y'all's conversations with continuing
conversation with Dr. Pitzky after uh
the presentation from last month that
thank you and the the insurability part
is is huge and so thank you again for
y'all working on that part because I
know that that's going to help uh
definitely
bring down the cost for the program to
patients and so it's something that
needs to always be at the forefront of
this is to ensure that the program can
be uh eligible for insurability to the
maximum extent that it can be. So, thank
you very much for for doing that. Uh, as
you can see, there's uh lots of there's
lots of work to go on and uh this is I
mean I know a lot of people think like
whoa wow this is dry but this is kind of
I mean I know the program is exciting
but this is really an exciting part of
it. um this uh for th for for those of
you that really get excited around
research and and continuous improvement.
Um I really encourage you to to jump
into some of these intersectional work
groups that these these uh leaders are
are doing because what Gregory and like
I said Danielle and Dr. Brown and
everybody are talking about are these
kind of important things that we can
build into it as best practices, as
ideas, as information into it. So,
please um uh and and please drop into
the chat box your email address if
people wanted to reach out and say like,
"Hey, I'd like to I'd like to be part of
these conversations so that that way
September 11th when we come back again,
um y'all's team can present some of the
uh work for this uh consensus part. So,
that's kind of what we have on our
calendar so far. I will probably start
to work with DO to slug some times on
the calendar for like October, November
as well. Um uh because right now these
are the only dates set and so we're at
the end of our our run that I pre set on
the calendar but uh I'll probably be
including a few more as we know that we
need to move forward with it. Um so at
this time this kind of leads us to the
last part which is the uh public comment
time. So I turn this over to everybody
that is on the call that we have some
time left for you to share. Um, this is
kind of your open floor if you will and
uh, we would love to hear from you. If
you can unmute your microphone by
raising your hand, we'll unmute your
microphone for you. Uh, everybody gets
three minutes to share during their open
mic time. And if you can't open your
microphone or raise your hand, then
please feel free to adopt it into the
chat and I'll read it into the record as
well. So uh at this time again as I said
please do feel free raise your hand uh
and we will unmute you or drop it into
the chat for your public comment time
and Dominic just dropped into the chat
also a way that you can uh raise your
hand at this time and don't forget that
uh Gregor Evans introduced his email
there. Interstitial work groups will be
Mondays at noon through the month of
August.
And then just in case I'm also going to
put into the chat for everybody if you
don't feel comfortable or you something
comes up in the next couple hours where
you say oh I should have thought about
and you wanted to include it in the
record um I just put the information
about how to submit written public
comments.
>> Thank you. Perfect. Thank you very much.
The email address there is also on the
screen for you and in the chat box how
to submit uh your public comments to
this meeting.
Okay
Garcia in the chat this may be a bit off
topic so if it can't be covered in this
meeting that's fine. Is there going to
be any active research in micro doing?
Uh and so I'll kind of give just a quick
brief information on that. Um and so at
this time the program is not uh this is
not a micro doing program which would
mean home use outside of facilities that
are deemed unless it's for example
through the rules. And so Dominic is on
and can you kind of share a little bit
more about that?
>> Yeah, I I mean you kind of covered that
right there Dan. Um but basically it's
the program has does not yet have the
research funding and um so at this point
u unless there are other uh researchers
who are out there who are looking into
micro doing which I know there are some
around the country but the program
itself is not going to be doing that
kind of research. Now again if down the
road there are funds uh in the research
fund then we would be doing RFPs of
course to uh send that on out for that
type of research and that is one of the
topics that has come up multiple times.
>> Thank you
and Gregory Evans.
I care a lot about micro doing. Um this
program is not designed for that. Um one
of the things that we can do is if we
extend our screening information, we can
collect data points on um what that
individual may have been doing outside
of the program indiv uh per personal
work that they've been doing. people are
talking about disclosing
um personal use um in their screening
data and um starting to collect
information about that and if people end
up disclosing that during about their
process of integration we can if the
department can allow for that type of um
personal use disclosure data capturing
lots of complicated [laughter]
uh areas stuff around this Um but if
there is a system that can be that can
start to record um what people are doing
outside of the
container that we are measuring um
[clears throat] essentially putting
those in as baseline uh data points then
we can start to be create the framework
for beginning to study some of that
stuff. So even though it's not really
something that the program will guide
on, it may be something that people
integrate with and that's not the
decision or the purview of the
department. But if the data point is
collected, we can start to recognize
patterns of efficacy. And I don't think
that we're more than a year or so away
from
having the capacity in here in New
Mexico or in other spaces for larger
micro doing studies. I look forward to
that.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else with public comment? Like I
said, please raise your hand and drop
into the chat if you have anything.
Okay, not seeing any. I appreciate
everybody's time today. Uh, thank you
very much for again coming to another
Friday meeting with us and again I hope
to see lots of y'all back here on
September 11th so that we can go over
the core extended data set framework and
really appreciate your your time, your
attention, your comments and everything
especially getting consensus around the
harm reduction quality improvement
framework. So again, thank you very much
for all of your work on that and those
that created the work and those that
voted on the work. So, thank you guys
very much
>> and on behalf of the department, thank
you as well. Um, just this was excellent
work and thank you everybody who's been
involved.
So, I hope everybody has a great rest of
your Friday and weekend.
>> Thanks everyone.